<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book id="top-of-user-guide">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Grotag User Guide</title>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>Amigaguide</keyword>

      <keyword>view convert</keyword>

      <keyword>pretty</keyword>

      <keyword>DocBook</keyword>

      <keyword>HTML</keyword>
    </keywordset>

    <copyright>
      <year>2008-2016</year>

      <holder>Thomas Aglassinger</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
      copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU Free
      Documentation License".</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <releaseinfo>$Revision: 231 $</releaseinfo>

    <author>
      <firstname>Thomas</firstname>

      <surname>Aglassinger</surname>
    </author>
  </bookinfo>

  <preface id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Grotag views Amigaguide documents or converts them to HTML and
    DocBook XML. Additionally it can validate and pretty print such
    documents.</para>

    <para>Amigaguide is a file format and application for AmigaOS<footnote>
        <para>The original Amigaguide is still available from any Aminet
        mirror, for example <ulink
        url="http://aminet.net/text/hyper/aguide34.lha"/>.</para>
      </footnote>. It enables to author and view hypertext documentation to
    some extend comparable to HTML or WinHelp. Most of the online
    documentation written for Amiga applications or about developing Amiga
    applications uses Amigaguide. Outside of AmigaOS however Amigaguide is
    unused and consequently hardly any viewers exist.</para>

    <para>Although most Amigaguide documents are not particular useful without
    access to an Amiga (real or emulated), occasionally a need arises to read
    such documentation on other platforms. Grotag is designed to address this
    need. It allows to convert Amigaguide documents to the platform
    independent HTML format, for which viewers exist on any reasonably modern
    system. Furthermore you can convert to DocBook, a format popular for
    technical documentations, allowing to bring along existing manuals into
    the 21st century for further editing.</para>

    <para>Grotag is written in Java (version 1.5 or later), which is supported
    by many current platforms such as Mac OS X (version 10.5 or later),
    Windows and Linux to name just a few.</para>

    <para>To find out what is new in this version, see the <link
    linkend="changes">revision history</link>. For updates and support, visit
    the Grotag homepage at <ulink
    url="http://grotag.sourceforge.net/">http://grotag.sourceforge.net</ulink>.</para>
  </preface>

  <chapter id="installation">
    <title>Installation</title>

    <section id="download">
      <title>Mac OS X</title>

      <para>For Mac OS X, visit <ulink
      url="http://grotag.sourceforge.net/">http://grotag.sourceforge.net</ulink>
      and download <filename>Grotag-x.y-z.dmg</filename>, where
      <filename>x.y.z</filename> refers to the current version number. Double
      click the disk archive to mount its contents as new device and open it
      in the Finder. It contains an application named Grotag resp. Grotag.app.
      Simply drag and drop this application in any folder you like to launch
      it from, for example <filename>/Applications</filename> or
      <filename>~/Applications</filename>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Other platforms</title>

      <para>For other platforms, visit <ulink
      url="http://grotag.sourceforge.net/">http://grotag.sourceforge.net</ulink>
      and download <filename>Grotag-x.y.zip</filename>, where
      <filename>x.y.z</filename> refers to the current version number. After
      extracting the archive, you should see at least the following
      files:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><filename>Grotag.jar</filename> - The application Java
          archive.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><filename>license.txt</filename> - A text file describing your
          rights related to Grotag. In short: It is an Open Source application
          and you do not have to pay money for it.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Now simply move Grotag.jar to a folder from where you want to
      start it. Under Windows, this could be in <filename>C:\Programe
      Files</filename>, under Unix it might be
      <filename>/usr/local/bin</filename> or
      <filename>~/bin</filename>.</para>

      <para>To launch Grotag from most Desktop environments, simply double
      click <filename>Grotag.jar</filename>. In case this does not work you
      have to use the command line as described in <xref
      linkend="command-line-usage"/>.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>The user interface</title>

    <para>This chapter describes how to perform common tasks with Grotag using
    the graphical user interface. This provides a comfortable way to access
    most functions using the mouse and keyboard. For repetitive tasks and
    automatization a probably better choice is described in <xref
    linkend="command-line-usage"/>.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Launch Grotag</title>

      <para>To launch Grotag under Mac OS X, simply double click the
      application icon or drop a <filename>*.guide</filename> file on
      it.</para>

      <para>To launch Grotag on most other platforms, simply double click
      <filename>Grotag.jar</filename> on the desktop.</para>

      <para>In case this does not work, open a terminal window (console) and
      enter:</para>

      <para><userinput>java -jar .../path/to/Grotag.jar</userinput></para>

      <para>Soon after that Grotag should present you an empty window.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Open an Amigaguide document</title>

      <para>In order to read an Amigaguide document, you have to open one
      using the menu entry <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>

          <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>. In the resulting dialog select the file and click the
      <guibutton>Open</guibutton> button. Grotag loads the document, including
      all linked documents. For complex guides (such as the Amiga ROM Kernel
      Reference Manuals) this may take a while. Watch the progress bar in the
      lower right corner of the window to estimate how long it still going to
      take.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Browse a document</title>

      <para>Once the document has been opened, you can browse it. As
      Amigaguide is a hyper text format just like HTML, viewers for it are
      fairly similar to web browsers. A major difference however is that
      Amigaguide automatically relates previous and next pages, so it is
      easily possible to sequentially browse a document with a standardized
      user interface. Furthermore authors can specify special pages containing
      a table of contents, an index, or a help page.</para>

      <para>Grotag offers several toolbar buttons and menu items to easily
      access all these pages, refer to <xref linkend="commands.browse"/> for
      details.</para>

      <table>
        <title id="commands.browse">Browsing a document</title>

        <tgroup cols="4">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Task</entry>

              <entry>Toolbar icon</entry>

              <entry>Menu entry</entry>

              <entry>Related Amigaguide command</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Browse back and forward through pages previously
              viewed.</entry>

              <entry><mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/back.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject><mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/forward.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry/>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Browse through the pages in sequential order. In case
              these buttons are greyed out, you are already at the first or
              last page. In case both of these buttons are greyed out, the
              document has only one page.</entry>

              <entry><mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/next.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject><mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/previous.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject></entry>

              <entry><menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>Go</guimenu>

                  <guimenuitem>Next</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>, <menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>Go</guimenu>

                  <guimenuitem>Previous</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice></entry>

              <entry><code>@next</code>, <code>@previous</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Go to the contents page for the current page. In case
              this button is greyed out, the author did not specify a contents
              page.</entry>

              <entry><mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/contents.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject></entry>

              <entry><menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>Go</guimenu>

                  <guimenuitem>Contents</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice></entry>

              <entry><code>@contents</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Go to the page the document initially opened
              with.</entry>

              <entry><mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/home.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry/>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Show the index page of the current document. In case this
              button is greyed out, the author did not specify an index
              page.</entry>

              <entry><mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/index.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject></entry>

              <entry><menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>Go</guimenu>

                  <guimenuitem>Index</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice></entry>

              <entry><code>@index</code></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Go to the help page for this particular guide. Unlike the
              Commodore Amigaguide application, Grotag does not provide a
              default help explaining the controls. In case this button is
              greyed out, the author did not specify a help page.</entry>

              <entry><mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/help.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject></entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry><code>@help</code></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Export a document to a different format</title>

      <para>In order to read a document without an Amigaguide reader, you can
      export it to HTML or XHTML by using the menu entry <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>

          <guimenuitem>Export</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>. After you choose a base folder for the converted
      documents, Grotag creates a folder with the same name as the Amigaguide
      document without the suffix ".guide".</para>

      <para>Additionally you can export to DocBook, which is useful if you
      want to integrate the information stored in the Amigaguide in an
      existing DocBook documentation. Be aware though that the DocBook variant
      has all the formatting information removed.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="command-line-usage">
    <title>Command line usage</title>

    <section id="command-line-launch">
      <title>Launch Grotag</title>

      <para>To launch Grotag from the command line, open a terminal window
      (console) and enter:</para>

      <para><userinput>java -jar .../path/to/Grotag.jar
      --help</userinput></para>

      <para>Replace "<filename>.../path/to/</filename>" by the location of the
      folder you extracted <filename>Grotag.zip</filename> to and where
      <filename>Grotag.jar</filename> is located.</para>

      <para>As a result, you should see a short description of the options you
      can pass to Grotag. Don't worry about them now, all of them will be
      explained later in this chapter.</para>

      <para>Because it is somewhat boring to type that much each time you want
      to launch Grotag, it is recommended to define a console alias. In bash,
      simply enter:</para>

      <para><userinput>alias grotag="java -jar
      .../path/to/Grotag.jar"</userinput></para>

      <para>After that, you can simply run</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --help</userinput></para>

      <para>to get same result as before. To avoid having to retype the alias
      each time you open a new terminal, add it to the shell startup file (for
      example <filename>~/.bashrc</filename> or
      <filename>~/.profile</filename> depending on your platform.)</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Show help and other information</title>

      <para>To read a short description of all options available for Grotag,
      run:</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --help</userinput></para>

      <para>To learn which version of Grotag you are using, run:</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --version</userinput></para>

      <para>To obtain information about Grotag's license, run:</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --license</userinput></para>
    </section>

    <section id="command-line-validate">
      <title>Validate Amigaguide documents</title>

      <para>To validate an Amigaguide document named
      <filename>some.guide</filename>, run:</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --validate some.guide</userinput></para>

      <para>In case Grotag detects any inconsistencies, it will report what it
      would have done in order to fix them. This isn't necessarily what you
      would have done to fix them, but still shows exactly where something is
      wrong.</para>

      <para>If you trust Grotag to do the right thing, you can let it fix the
      reported issues by using the command line option
      <userinput>--pretty</userinput>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="command-line-pretty">
      <title>Pretty print and fix Amigaguide documents</title>

      <para>Amigaguide never came with an authoring tool or a formal
      specification of the format. Consequently many existing Amigaguide
      documents contain little inconsistencies the rather lenient Amigaguide
      application stilled displayed without any trouble.</para>

      <para>Grotag takes a different approach: it points even tiny little
      errors, and makes an attempt to fix it in a way that preserves the
      content while resulting in an documents that does not have the issue
      anymore.</para>

      <para>Furthermore Grotag cleans up formatting and upper/lower case in
      mark up.</para>

      <warning>
        <para>Note that the original version of the Amigaguide document will
        be overwritten and consequently be lost unless you made a backup copy
        of it before applying <userinput>--pretty</userinput>.</para>
      </warning>

      <para>In order to clean up the file <filename>ugly.guide</filename>,
      run:</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --pretty ugly.guide</userinput></para>

      <para>In case you want to clean up multiple files, you can pass all of
      them along at once.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="command-line-html">
      <title>Convert Amigaguide documents to HTML</title>

      <para>To convert an Amigaguide document named
      <filename>some.guide</filename> to a set of HTML documents, run:</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --html some.guide</userinput></para>

      <para>This creates a folder <filename>some</filename> in the current
      folder, which contains a <filename>*.html</filename> file for each node.
      The file for the main node is always called
      <filename>index.html</filename>.</para>

      <para>To store the output in a different folder, specify it as a second
      option. For example, to store the HTML version of
      <filename>some.guide</filename> in <filename>~/guides</filename>,
      run:</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --docbook some.guide ~/guides</userinput></para>

      <para>To start reading, open
      <filename>~/guides/some/index.html</filename>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="command-line-docbook">
      <title>Convert Amigaguide documents to DocBook XML</title>

      <para>To convert an Amigaguide document named
      <filename>some.guide</filename> to a DocBook XML file named
      <filename>some.xml</filename>, run:</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --docbook some.guide</userinput></para>

      <para>To use a different name for the output file, specify a second
      file. For example, to store the DocBook version of
      <filename>some.guide</filename> in <filename>other.xml</filename>,
      run:</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --docbook some.guide
      other.xml</userinput></para>

      <para>The DocBook output does not preserve any formatting command like
      <code>@{b}</code>, <code>@{fg shine}</code> and so in. It only
      reproduces the structure of the document. Each guide represents a
      chapter, and each node is a section. If the Amigaguide document
      specified in the command line links to other documents, they will be
      included in the DocBook output as additional chapters.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="acknowledgement">
    <title>Acknowledgment</title>

    <para>The following resources have been helpful for developing
    Grotag:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://homepage.mac.com/sroy/mrjadapter/">MRJAdapter</ulink>
        allows to integrate Java applications nicely into Mac OS X.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.everaldo.com/crystal/">Crystal</ulink> is
        the icon set use in the toolbar.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://safalra.com/other/amigaguide/">Salfara's
        website</ulink> documents the Amigaguide format quite
        diligently.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <command>agr</command> command line Amigaguide reader
        includes a couple of interesting test documents.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="changes">
    <title>Changes</title>

    <para>This chapter describes improvements compared to earlier versions of
    Grotag.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Version 0.3.0, xx-Nov-2016</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Removed special support for Mac OS X. Grotag still runs under
          Mac OS X but there are not features like dragging and dropping
          documents on the icon. The reason for this is that in recent years
          Apple gradually removed support for Java. Consequently packages like
          MRJAdapter have not been updated anymore.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added support for Euro character by changing encoding from
          ISO-8859-1 to cp1252.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Version 0.2.0, 04-Jan-2012</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Fixed launching under Mac OS X 10.6, which could not execute
          the included PPC Java launcher.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added menu item <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>File</guimenu>

              <guimenuitem>Export</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice> to export the document currently viewing to other
          formats.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added GUI settings to be preserved using the Java Preferences
          API.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="v0.1.1">
      <title>Version 0.1.1, 05-Oct-2008</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Fixed <guibutton>Back</guibutton> button, which seemingly
          navigated to random pages.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Changed toolbar buttons to use icons instead of text
          labels.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> button.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added proper About dialog.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="v0.1.0">
      <title>Version 0.1.0, 19-Sep-2008</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Initial release.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
